- [Narrator] When we create
a grid with CSS Grid Layout,
we can use a variety of different
ways to size the tracks.
We'll take a look at a
grid specific sizing method
in the next lesson, but first,
let's have a better look at
how different sizing values and keywords
work for grid.
I'm continuing to use the files from
the last lesson so Basics
to HTML and Basics .CSS.
And in our last lesson,
we used pixels to size our tracks.
We can however use any valid length unit
so that might be viewport units, ems,
or any other unit you might want to use,
they're all possible.
So perhaps we could
change this first column.
To 20vw.
And we might want to make this one 12 em.
So any of the length units
that you're familiar with,
you can use those.
You can also use percentages.
When you use a percentage for a track size
it will be calculated from the size
of the grid container.
Therefore a 20% column track
is going to be 20% of the width.
Percentages are also valid
for the gap property.
You can use auto for your track sizing
and that's actually the
default track sizing
if you don't specify a size for track.
You can really think of auto as being
kind of big enough to fit the content.
So when we've got an auto sized track,
it will keep expanding to take up
as much space for the content to fill in.
It's worth noting if
you use auto for tracks
where there is some extras
or size in that dimension,
for example if we make
a column track auto,
you can see that it stretches.
It's the only one of these tracks
that will actually
stretch if there's extra
space in the grid container,
it will stretch out and take it up.
The auto keyword is a
kind of intrinsic sizing
and what that means is
it looks at the content
and it decides how big it needs to be
based on the content size.
And we've also got some newer
intrinsic sizing keywords.
Now these aren't just for grid,
they can be used elsewhere,
they can be used for width and things.
But they've got the best
browser support in grid,
so they're really nice
to use for grid layout.
Anywhere that grid is support
you can also use these keywords.
So let's have a quick look at those.
Now the first of the keywords
we're going to look at
is called min-content.
So if we make all of our
tracks min-content size,
just like this.
You can see what happens
to the display here.
They've gone down to the
smallest they can do.
So at track three here, has basically got
as small as, I think,
the word content here
is the longest word.
And so that's holding the track
as big as it needs to be.
So that's kind of the
min-content size of our tracks.
We have another keyword which is
sort of the reverse of
this, that's max-content.
So if we set our three tracks
to be max-content size,
now you can see that the
tracks have got as big
as they can be.
So what's happened here
is the string inside
track three has unraveled and it's
getting as long as it needs to be,
and then that's how
big that track becomes.
Now, this would cause overflows
if the grid container was smaller,
if you had a lot of text in there,
this could cause a scroll bar to poke out
of the side of the grid.
That's the max-content size.
And we have a third, which
is called fit-content.
And you pass a value into fit-content,
so let's do that.
Let's say fit-content
and we're going to say
10em, so whatever you pass in,
let's do this to all of them,
and then we can see what
happens when we save this.
So what fit-content does is it
tries to go to max-content,
so it tries to make the track
as big as it can be,
but if it hits the value
that you've passed in,
it doesn't grow any more after that point.
So you can see that our first two tracks
are just laying out
their max-content size,
and then the track three
has much more content,
and so it gets to that
value, it gets to 10em
and then it starts to wrap,
it gets kind of clumped at that value.
So fit-content is quite a useful one.
You can use that to allow things to be
as flexible within limits.
You can sort of say yes
I would like you to grow
up to this point and then I'm gonna
stop you growing and that stops
having the overflows.
So that's quite a useful
track sizing function to use.
So that's really what you need to know
about track sizing with
existing length units,
things from values and units.
In the next lesson though,
we'll have a look at a track sizing method
which is very specific to grid layout.